A Guide to the Charles Augustus Strong Papers FA087
Rockefeller Archive Center
Charles Augustus Strong papers
1877-1939, 1961, n.d.
Rockefeller Archive Center
Strong, Charles Augustus
James, William
Santayana, George
FA087
3.8 Cubic Feet 11 Boxes
4 cubic ft.
Arrangement note
The Strong papers are arranged in five series:
Series 1 - Personal Correspondence; Series 2 - Professional Correspondence; Series 3 - Writings; Series 4 - Writings of Others; Series 5 - Miscellaneous Papers
Within the correspondence series, letters have been retained in their original order, in runs of Incoming and Outgoing correspondence. Series 3 - Writings is arranged alphabetically by title. Series 4 - Writings of Others is arranged alphabetically by author. In Series 5 - Miscellaneous Papers, materials are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Augustus Strong, a philosopher of the American school of critical realists, was born in Haverhill, Massachusetts on November 28, 1862. He was the eldest of six children born to the Rev. Augustus Hopkins Strong and Harriet Savage Strong. In 1865 Rev. Strong, a Baptist minister, became pastor of First Church in Cleveland, Ohio. During the years 1865 to 1872, the Strongs grew well acquainted with the family of John D. Rockefeller, Sr., their fellow parishioners. In 1872 Rev. Strong was named President of the Rochester Theological Seminary in his hometown of Rochester, New York. It was there that the young Charles Strong received his early schooling. In the fall of 1877, Strong enrolled at Phillips Exeter Academy in Exeter, New Hampshire. He excelled in the study of Latin and Greek, played football and baseball, and served as editor of the school paper. In July 1881, Strong sailed for Europe to attend the Gutersloh Gymnasium in Gutersloh, Germany. On returning to America in 1883, he entered the University of Rochester, where he obtained his A.B. in 1884 and the LL.D. in 1919. Fulfilling a long-standing desire, he enrolled in Harvard College in the fall of 1884, graduating with a second A.B. in 1885.
Strong's Harvard experience proved to be a turning point. He came under the influence of the pragmatist philosopher and psychologist William James, and with his fellow student and life-long friend, George Santayana, founded the Harvard Philosophical Club. After a year (1885-86) at Rochester Theological Seminary, Strong embarked for Berlin on a James Walker Fellowship from Harvard, which by mutual agreement, he shared with Santayana. By this time, Strong had suffered a loss of faith and rejected the ministerial career which his father had envisioned for him. In Berlin, he studied psychology, philosophy, and physiology with professors Karl Stumpf and Friedrich Paulsen.
From 1887 to 1889, Strong served as part-time instructor in philosophy at Cornell University, then returned to Europe for studies at Berlin, Paris and Freiburg in 1889-90. On March 22, 1889, he married Bessie Rockefeller (1866-1906), the eldest daughter of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. They had one child, Margaret Strong de Cuevas (1897-1985).
In 1890 Strong became a docent at Clark University and in 1892 was appointed associate professor of psychology at the University of Chicago, where he remained until 1895. He served as lecturer in psychology at Columbia University from 1895 until 1903 and as professor of psychology from 1903 to 1910.
In 1903, Bessie Strong's failing health necessitated the Strongs' transfer to Paris, where Strong remained on leave without pay from Columbia University. After his wife's death on November 14, 1906, Strong settled in Fiesole, Italy in the villa known as "Le Balze." There, he raised his daughter and continued to study, write, and receive visitors. Strong died on January 23, 1940 in Fiesole.
Strong's writings include "Why the Mind Has A Body" (1903), "The Origins of Consciousness" (1918), "Essays in Critical Realism" (1920), "The Wisdom of the Beasts" (1921), "A Theory of Knowledge" (1923), "Essays on the Natural Origin of the Mind" (1930), and "A Creed for Sceptics" (1936).
Scope and Contents note
The Charles A. Strong Papers document the thought of philosopher and psychologist Charles Strong (1862-1940) and his friendships with George Santayana (1863-1952), William James (1842-1910), and a circle of academic philosophers known as the "critical realists". The critical realists worked within the school of American pragmatism originated by Charles Sanders Peirce (1839-1914) and popularized by William James. Also present in the collection are two letters from American novelist, Edith Wharton (1924, n.d.) and a small group of letters (1921-1935) to Strong from the English writer, Violet Paget (Vernon Lee, 1856-1935), documenting the close friendship between the two expatriates. The papers span the years 1877 to 1939, but the bulk of the material dates between 1906 and 1939. The collection was transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1994 by the donor.
Little information is available in these papers about Strong's personal life. There are scattered references to his wife, Bessie Rockefeller, and her illnesses, but there is no correspondence from her in this collection. Strong's relationship with the Rockefeller family can only be surmised from these documents. There are two letters from his father-in-law, John D. Rockefeller, Sr. (1927, 1933); the first relates to the disposition of Bessie Rockefeller's estate, the second to an allowance for Margaret, Strong's daughter. A 1916 letter from Rockefeller to Strong's father, Augustus H. Strong expresses the wish that the Strongs resettle in America, "instead of isolating themselves from their family, and making other connections with strangers." The bulk of Senior's correspondence with Charles and Margaret Strong is located in the Rockefeller Family Archives, Record Group 1, John D. Rockefeller Papers, Correspondence Series-Personal. Outgoing correspondence from the letterbooks is available on microfilm. There is incoming correspondence from Bessie Rockefeller Strong (1891-1894), Charles Strong (1886-1894), and Augustus Strong (1879-1894). In Record Group 2, (Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller), Series H, Friends and Services (Friends and Relations section), there is one folder of correspondence (1886-1911) from both John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and their associates to Charles and Bessie (1886-1911). Also available in Record Group 2, in the personal papers of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., is correspondence (1881, 1886-1925) between John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Augustus and Kate Strong, Charles' sister. In the Strong papers described here, George Santayana's letters indirectly provide information about Margaret Strong and her husband, George de Cuevas, as Santayana remained a lifelong friend to the Strongs.
Related Archival Materials note
Rockefeller Family Archives
Record Group 1 - John D. Rockefeller Papers Correspondence Series - Personal
Record Group 2 - Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller Series H - Friends and Services, Friends and Relations section Series Z - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal Papers
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
File Plan note
Former Classification: 51
Philosophy and religion; Religion
- Personal Correspondence, 1877-1889, 1903-1939; 51/1; 1.2 Cubic Feet 3 Boxes
  Arrangement note
  The letters in this series have been retained in their original order, in runs of incoming and outgoing correspondence.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1, Personal Correspondence, contains four folders of detailed letters (1877-85, 1891, 1939) from Strong to his family, written largely between the ages of fifteen and twenty-five. In them, Strong gives news of his scholastic achievements at Phillips Exeter Academy, the Gutersloh Gymnasium in Germany, and Harvard College. After his father opposed his first bid to attend Harvard, Strong wrote, "I think I have a moderately good faculty of putting up with my lot." The bulk of Strong's incoming correspondence consists of letters from his father (1910-1921) reporting on family activities in Rochester, New York and his frequent travels. The few letters from his mother, Harriet Strong, are interfiled with those of Augustus Strong.
  - Strong, Augustus H. (Incoming), 1912-1915, 1918-1921, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Achilles, Paul Strong, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - de Cuevas, George, 1934, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Fowler, E. H., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Norton, Mrs. M. B., 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Prentice, Alta Rockefeller, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Prentice, E. Parmalee, 1903, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Rockefeller, John D. Sr., 1916, 1927, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Sewall, Rev. Charles G., 1919, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Augustus H., 1915-1921 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Harriet Louise Savage, 1911-1913, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Henry A., 1918 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, John, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Julia, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Kate, 1903, 1911-1914, 1919-1921, 1936, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Laura, 1914, 1920-1921, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Incoming Correspondence - Strong, Margaret, 1911, 1938, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Outgoing Correspondence, 1877-1885, 1891, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Outgoing Correspondence, 1877-1885, 1891, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Outgoing Correspondence, 1877-1885, 1891, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Outgoing Correspondence, 1877-1885, 1891, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Strong, Charles A. - Outgoing Correspondence, 1877-1885, 1891, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Third Party Correspondence, 1904, 1912, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    "Dot", n.d. Hovey, Henrietta B., 1904 Rockefeller, Laura Spelman, 1912? Sewall, Kate Strong, 1904
- Professional Correspondence, 1889-1939; 51/2; 2 Cubic Feet 4 Boxes
  Series 2, Professional Correspondence, fills Boxes 4 through 8 and contains Strong's correspondence with philosophers and writers. Strong's correspondents include Bernard and Mary Berenson, Henri Bergson, Alfred Binet, John Dewey, G. Lowes Dickinson, John Galsworthy, William James, Arthur O. Lovejoy, John Masefield, G. E. Moore, Friedrich Paulsen (1 letter), Charles S. Peirce (2 letters), Ralph Barton Perry (2 letters), Walter Rauschenbusch, Bertrand Russell, George Santayana, F. C. S. Schiller, and Paul Shorey. Among his most faithful colleagues and critics were Durant Drake (Vassar College), Dickinson S. Miller (Columbia), James Bissett Pratt (Williams College), A. K. Rogers (Yale) and Roy Wood Sellars (University of Michigan). Strong's outgoing correspondence includes a packet entitled "My Letters to Philosophers" (1902-12).
  George Santayana's correspondence with Strong, located in Series 2, is the largest single correspondence in the collection. The letters are uninterrupted for the period 1900 to 1939 and fill twenty folders. Most of the letters were written after 1912 during extended sojourns in France, Italy, Germany, and Spain. Santayana's letters are warm and full of personal anecdote, and report on the books he is reading as well as the progress of his own writings, including "The Realm of Matter" (1930), "The Realm of Truth" (1937), "The Realm of Spirit" (1940), and the novel, "The Last Puritan" (1939). Although they remained loyal friends, Strong and Santayana continually disagreed over the scope and limits of perception. Their philosophical differences gradually took on a personal edge. After a 1938 meeting in Rome, which led to an altercation, Santayana wrote that he and Strong had fallen "out of sympathy on almost every current subject." In 1939, he declared, "Your presuppositions as to what can and what cannot excite consciousness are not such as I feel any need of making." Strong's letters to Santayana fill three folders and consist mainly of transcript drafts of letters for the years 1930, 1932 and 1933 concerning philosophical subjects.
  The letters of William James to Charles Strong fill seven folders and are largely uninterrupted for the period 1898 to 1910, the year of James' death. In his letters, James discusses materialism, his reactions to Strong's writings, books he is reading, his teaching load, travel plans, family life, and the precarious state of his health. He describes in 1905 his first encounter with French philosopher Henri Bergson. Writing on 6 February 1906 from Palo Alto, where he was lecturing at Stanford University, he gives a lively account of his reaction to the San Francisco earthquake. Strong's letters to James fill one folder. Two letters (1889), written from Berlin, offer a theory of materialism explaining the relationship between the mind and the body, in which the human mind is a product of natural processes. Strong's theory found formal expression in his first book, "Why the Mind has a Body" (1903).
  - Incoming Correspondence (A), 1914, 1929, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Incoming Correspondence (B), 1903-1904, 1915, 1918-1919, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Berenson, Mary, 1911-1912, 1916-1917, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Bergson, Henri, 1904-1910, 1918, 1923, 1926, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Binet, Alfred, 1906, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Incoming Correspondence (C), 1903, 1906, 1908, 1913, 1930, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Carr, Herbert Wildon, 1911-1913, 1919, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Cattell, James McKeen, 1904-1906 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Cohen, Morris R., 1919, 1930, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Cutting, Sybil Lubbock, 1915-1917, 1937, 1939, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Incoming Correspondence (D), 1903, 1905, 1909, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Incoming Correspondence (G), 1904, 1915, 1920, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Drake, Durant, 1910, 1914-1917, 1926-1927, 1930, 1932, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Incoming Correspondence (F), 1903, 1905, 1908, 1919-1921, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Incoming Correspondence (H-K), 1903-1904, 1920, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, Alice H., 1909-1911 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, Henry, Jr., 1911, 1922, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Incoming Correspondence - James, William, 1889, 1895, 1898-1900, 1902-1910, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Incoming Correspondence (L), 1918, 1921, 1925, 1928, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Laird, John, 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Lovejoy, Arthur O., 1919, 1921, 1925-1926, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Incoming Correspondence (M) (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Masefield, John, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Incoming Correspondence - McDougall, William, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Michelson, A. A., 1921, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Miller, Dickinson S., 1900-1901, 1905-1906, 1914, 1919-1934, 1939, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Miller, Dickinson S., 1900-1901, 1905-1906, 1914, 1919-1934, 1939, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Miller, Dickinson S., 1900-1901, 1905-1906, 1914, 1919-1934, 1939, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Montague, William P., 1923, 1926-1928, 1931, 1937, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Osler, Sir William, 1916, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Incoming Correspondence (P), 1889, 1903-1904, 1916, 1919, 1924, 1928, 1932, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Paget, Violet (Vernon Lee), 1921-1935 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Pratt, James B., 1917-1921, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Incoming Correspondence (R), 1920-1921, 1930, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Rauschenbusch, Walter, 1903, 1911, 1913, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Rogers, A. K., 1903-1904, 1917, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Russell, Bertrand, 1930, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Russell, Elisabeth, Countess, 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Incoming Correspondence (S), 1903-1933, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1889-1891, 1895, 1900-1926 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1937-1939, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Schiller, F. C. S. (Ferdinand Canning Scott), 1904-1934, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Scott, Geoffrey, 1916, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Selety, Franz, 1921-1923 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Incoming Correspondence (T), 1903 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Incoming Correspondence (V), 1904, 1906, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Incoming Correspondence (W), 1903-1904, 1907-1908, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Wharton, Edith, 1924, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Woods, James H., 1930-1931 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Incoming Correspondence - Unidentified, 1889, 1903, 1919, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Letters, 1902-1907 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Letters, 1902-1907 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Letters, 1908, 1912-1913, 1921-1938, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Letters, 1908, 1912-1913, 1921-1938, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Letters, 1908, 1912-1913, 1921-1938, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Letters, 1908, 1912-1913, 1921-1938, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Outgoing Correspondence (C-D), 1909-1910 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - James, William, 1889-1890, 1895, 1908, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - Outgoing Correspondence (L), 1920-1921, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Outgoing Correspondence (M), 1899, 1902, 1910-1911, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Moore, G. E., 1910-1911, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Outgoing Correspondence (R-S), 1913, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1890, 1900, 1903-1904, 1912, 1919, 1930, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1890, 1900, 1903-1904, 1912, 1919, 1930, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Santayana, George, 1890, 1900, 1903-1904, 1912, 1919, 1930, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - Outgoing Correspondence (W), 1903-1904 (Box 8, Folder 132)
- Writings, 1890-1939; 51/3; 0.2 Cubic Feet 1 Box